A Guide to the Papers of Alfred J. Swan collected by his student John Davison, 1894-1955
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Alfred J. Swan collected by his student John Davison, 1894-1955
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10093-e
This collection contains ca. 318 (3 Hollinger boxes, and 2 oversize boxes).
The Swan papers were collected by John Davison.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These items were given to the University of Virginia Library by Elizabeth Davison, Haverford, Pennsylvania, on September 27, 1999.
Biographical/Historical Information
According to one concert program, Albert J. Swan (1890-1970) was a member of an English family who settled in Russia, where he was born in 1890 at St. Petersburg, where he also attended the St. Petersburg Conservatory. He left to study law, languages and music at Oxford, England, emigrating to the United States in the 1920s. He taught first at the University of Virginia, and then jointly at Haverford and Swarthmore Colleges from 1926 until his retirement in 1959. Swan was first recognized as a writer on music and as a musicologist interested in the relationship between Russian church chant and folk song. His work as a composer produced "four piano sonatas, six quartets, and much liturgical choral music, written mostly to old Slavonic texts for the Orthodox church, including a complete setting of the extensive Orthodox service," among others.
Scope and Content Information
This addition to the papers of Alfred J. Swan (1890-1970), composer and the first professor of music at Haverford College, consists of ca. 318 items, ca. 1894-1995, primarily music manuscripts; sheet music; concert programs; newsclippings; articles; music catalogues and circulars; materials pertaining to an exhibit about Swan at the Music Library, Haverford College, and a Swan Centennial Concert; and miscellaneous items concerning Swan from the library of his student, John Davison.
Organization
The collection is organized with the non-musical material first (Box 1); music by Swan (Boxes 1-3); various non-Swan music (end of Box 3); oversize music by Swan (Oversize Box S-61) and oversize music by various students of Swan (Oversize Box S-62).
Contents List
- NON-MUSICAL MATERIAL
  - Articles About Peter Schickele 1967 May, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Catalogue of Alfred Swan's Musical Work - by John Davison n.d. (Box 1)
  - Concert Programs 1970-1971, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Materials for Alfred J. Swan Exhibit Music Library, Haverford College 1989 May-1990 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 1909, 1989-1900, 1995, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Music Catalogues 1952 & 1955 (Box 1)
  - Muscial Circulars - Tempo and The Musical Times1954 & 1956 (Box 1)
  - Newsclippings About Swan 1964 May, 1968 Nov, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Swan Centennial Concert (Nov 16 1990) - Ads & Programs 1990 Nov (Box 1)
  - Swan Centennial Concert (Nov 16, 1990) - Newsclippings 1990 Nov (Box 1)
  - Swan Centennial Concert (Nov 16, 1990) - Planning & Correspondence (Box 1)
- MUSICAL MATERIAL
  - Alma Redemptoris Mater for 4-part choir a cappella 1951 (Box 1)
  - Autumn fires(for three voices a cappella) 1965 (Box 1)
  - Beginning of the Liturgy- choral music (1 of 5) ca. 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - Beginning of the Liturgy- choral music (2 of 5) ca. 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - Beginning of the Liturgy- choral music (3 of 5) ca. 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - Beginning of the Liturgy- choral music (4 of 5) ca. 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - Beginning of the Liturgy- choral music (5 of 5) ca. 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - Blessed Is He(for mixed chorus) 1961 (Box 1)
  - Candlelighting Hymn n.d. (Box 1)
  - Canticles of the Eastern Church I 1976 (Box 1)
  - Dance With A Trumpet for piano four-hands 1931 (Box 1)
  - Eclogue for Viola and Piano 1968* (Box 2)
  - Folk-songs From Russia- Ten folk-songs for voice and piano as sung by peasants of Gorodishone (written 1936) 1939 (Box 2)
  - Gavotte for piano four-hands 1920 (Box 2)
  - Glorification of St. Nicholas for mixed chorus and two pianos 1943 (Box 2)
  - Into A Child's Album(for piano) 1949, 1960 (Box 2)
  - Into An Album(for piano) 1959 (Box 2)
  - Invocation to Clio(for piano) 1947 (Box 2)
  - Jane's Melodies(for piano) 1946 (Box 2)
  - Liadov Songs Arranged by Swan n.d. (Box 2)
  - Liturgical Canticles of the Eastern Church(10) - Boosey & Hawkes (written 1940-1957) 1956 & 1959 (Box 2)
  - Misc. Swan Music n.d. (Box 2)
  - (Two) Motets for Baritone and String Quartet or String Orchestra 1946-1948 (Box 2)
  - (Box 2)
  - Nunc Dimittis (Kiev Chant)(for voices, part of vespers and matins) 1961 (Box 2)
  - O Lux Beata(for three women's voices) 1960 (Box 2)
  - Old English Folk Songs 1920? (Box 2)
  - Pasadoble for oboe and piano (corrected copy) 1962 (Box 2)
  - Petite Suite de Ballet(Petite Suite de Danse for piano) 1953 (Box 2)
  - Pezzo Lugubre(fragment from a string quintet) 1947 (Box 2)
  - Prelude(for piano) 1970 (Box 2)
  - Ronde de Printemps(piano four-hands) 1950-1960 (Box 2)
  - Rondeau des Enfants(#1, for piano, written 1932) 1937 (Box 2)
  - Russian Choral Music (written 1940-1966) 1965-1970 (Box 2)
  - Russian Piece 1961 (Box 2)
  - Six Quartets- No. 1 in C (1936), No. 2 in D (with Flute) (1940) 1967* & 1968* (Box 2)
  - Six Quartets- No.3 (1950), No. 4 in b (1953) 1965* & 1966* (Box 2)
  - Six Quartets- No. 5 in a (1963), No. 6 in E flat (1964) 1966* & 1968* (Box 2)
  - Sonata No. 1 - In Una Parte(for piano, written 1932) 1937 (Box 2)
  - Sonata No. 2(for piano) n.d. (Box 2)
  - Sonate #3(new version) (for piano) 1944-1945 (Box 2)
  - Sonata No. 4 - Easter Sonata 1947 (Box 2)
  - Sonata (#5) K. 556 for piano solo 1958 (Box 2)
  - Sonata No. 2 for violin and piano (written 1968) 1970 (Box 3)
  - Song of Evening(for mixed voices) 1934 (Box 3)
  - Song of Glorification and Thanksgiving(for big chorus a cappella, written 1956) 1964 (Box 3)
  - Songs for one voice and piano - Nos. 13, 15, 16 & 19(words by R.L. Stevenson, Dowson, Blake, de la Mare) 1946-1956 (Box 3)
  - St. Luke XXIII, 39-43(for men's voices a cappella) 1958 (Box 3)
  - Sticheron for Annunciation for mixed chorus a cappella 1940 (Box 3)
  - The Highlander's Lament(also, Barbara Allen) 1968 (Box 3)
  - The Lenten Prayer of St. Ephrem the Syrian(for mezzo-soprano, baritone, viola, bassoon) 1962 (Box 3)
  - Three Christmas Songs(for voice and piano) 1957 (Box 3)
  - Three Pieces Based on Traditional Melodies for cello and piano 1943-1967 (Box 3)
  - Trio for Piano, Flute, and Clarinet(written 1932) 1936 (Box 3)
  - Two Choruses from the Liturgy- mixed chorus n.d. (Box 3)
  - T wo Kontakia to St. Nicholas(for voices) 1966 (Box 3)
  - Two Poems by John Masefield - Being Her Friend and The Gentle Lady(for voice and piano) 1914-1915 (Box 3)
  - Various Non-Swan Choral Music - Christmas 1900-1935 (Box 3)
  - Various Non-Swan Choral Music - Sacred 1897-1942 (Box 3)
  - Various Non-Swan Choral Music - Secular 1894-1956 (Box 3)
  - Various Non- Swan Music - some student dedications 1947, 1961-1967, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Vespers and Matins (Holy Liturgy of St. John Chrysostom)(for big chorus a cappella) 1960 (Box 3)
  - Vouchsafe, O Lord, thy heav'nly blessing(arrangement for men's voices) n.d. (Box 3)
  - The Christmas Game 1945, 1959* (Oversize S-61:1)
  - Trio-Sonata for 2 violins and piano 1966 (Oversize S-61:2)
  - Various Swan Music titles 1937-1964 (Oversize S-61:3)
    Includes the following titles:
    Albumblatt(1946*)
    Album of Pieces(written 1923-1956) (1964)
    Anglaise(with letter to John Davison) (1952)
    Glorification of St. Nicholas for 2 pianos; chorus and 2 pianos (1942 Dec & 1943)
  - Various Swan Music titles 1937-1964 (Oversize S-61:4)
    Into A Child's Album(1949)
    Invocation to Clio(1947)
    Jane's Melodies(1946)
    Prelude and Fugue for piano(1951)
    Rondeau des Enfants(1937)
  - Various Swan Music titles 1937-1964 (Oversize S-61:5)
    Sonata No. 3 (old version)(1944-1945)
    Sonata No. 4 - Easter Sonata(1947)
    Sonatine pour le piano(1953)
    The Holy Liturgy of St. John Chrysostom(1960)
    Wendy's Song(1954)
  - Music by Lawrance Collingwood ca. 1920-1930 (Oversize S-62:1)
    1930 Cherry-Ripe(1930)
    1930 Elegy(1930)
    1920 Exceeding Sorrow(1920)
    1920 June(1920)
    n.d. Mamble(n.d.)
    n.d. Nightingales(n.d.)
    n.d. "Not all in Vain"(n.d.)
    1930 November(1930)
    n.d. The Cloths of Heaven(n.d.)
    n.d. The Wood of Flowers(n.d.)
    n.d. Untitled "Rages, softly sweet..."(n.d.)
    n.d. When that I loved a Maiden(n.d.)
  - Various Swan Music titles (some student dedications) 1937-1968 (Oversize S-62:2)
    Contrapuntos sobre canciones populares catalanas- Bernhard Rouenstrunck (1955-1959)
    Minuet and Trio for Pianoforte- D.I. Swann (1937)
    Mipanta-Palamao- D.I. Swann (1948-1949)
    Nunc Dimittis (St. Simeon's Prayer)- Antony Bassoline (1967)
    Only Begotten Son- (Antony) Bassoline (n.d.)
    Prelude in G Minor- D.I. Swann (1947)
    Sonata in One Movement for Flute and Violincello- Jerome D. Goodman (1958)
    Sonatina in C#- W. Muir (1946)
    Second Piano Sonatina- Peter Schickele (1956)
    Te Deum Laudamus- Yury Arbatsky (1951)
    To One in Paradise-E.A. Poe- D.I. Swann (1942)
    Valse Joyeuse- Truman Bullard (1968)
    Unknown Title and Author in Russian (1962)
  - Various Non-Swan Music (some student dedications) n.d. (Oversize S-62:3)
    Introduction to "Renard"
    Legende de Saint Efflam (Basse Bretagne)- P.Ladmirault
    Macbeth Act III Scene II
    Revuici le printemps- P.Ladmirault
    Russian Title - Turchaninoff
    The Merchant's Daughter
    Turtle Dove- Peter Schickele
  - Cover made and designed for Alfred Swan by Rosalie L. Lane 1946 (Oversize S-62:4)